Guide to the Doris Bryn Papers, 1939-1998 and undated
The John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Doris Bryn papers 1939-1998 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Bryn, Doris.
6.0 Linear Feet 3000 Items
Doris Bryn (née Krehnbrink) was a prominent fashion and cover model during the 1940s-1960s and co-designer of several lines of fashion accessories with her husband Roger Vsn Schoyck under the brand names Roger Van S. and Mr. R.
The Doris Bryn Papers span the years 1939-1998 and includes correspondence, clippings, print advertisements, photographs, design sketches and garment labels that document Bryn's career as a professional cover and fashion model (for Conover, John Powers and Eileen Ford agencies) and as a designer of dresses, shoes, leather goods, jewelry and other fashion accessories under the lines Roger Van S. and Mr. R among others. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Doris Bryn Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2012.
Biographical Note
Doris Bryn (née Krehnbrink) was born in 1920 and attended the University of Cincinnati for two years before leaving for a full-time career as a fashion and cover model, working for New York agencies Conover, Eileen Ford, and John Powers. Bryn became a prominent cover model, and was featured on major publications like Vogue and Life magazines, as well as appearing as a subject for pulp fiction cover art. She met and married Roger Van Schoyck in the early 1940s and they started a line of fashion accessories under the name Roger Van S. in 1945. Early inventories focused on leather goods, but later the business expanded to include dresses, shoes, and jewelry. Initially the business ran as a craft cooperative employing disabled veterans, but production moved to Asia as demand increased. The business closed in the late 1980s and the Van Schoycks became real estate agents in New Jersey. Roger Van Schoyck died in 2007; Doris in 2010.
Collection Overview
The Doris Bryn Papers span the years 1939-1998 and includes correspondence, clippings, print advertisements, photographs, design sketches and garment labels that document Bryn's career as a professional cover and fashion model (for Conover, John Powers and Eileen Ford agencies) and as a designer of dresses, shoes, leather goods, jewelry and other fashion accessories under the lines Roger Van S. and Mr. R among others.
Collection Arrangement
Organized into the following series: General Files, Roger Van S. and Large Format Materials.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Van Schoyck, Doris
Advertising
Advertising -- Clothing and dress
Advertising -- History
Advertising -- History -- United States
Advertising -- History -- United States -- 20th century
Advertising -- Jewelry
Clothing and dress
Dressmaking
Fashion
Fashion -- United States
Fashion -- United States -- History
Fashion -- United States -- History -- 20th century
Fashion design
Fashion designers
Fashion designers -- United States
Fashion merchandising
Handbags
Jewelry
Jewelry making
Leather garments industry
Leather goods
Leather industry and trade
Leather industry and trade -- United States
Leather working
Leatherwork
Models (Persons)
New Jersey -- Commerce
Retail advertising
Retail marketing
Retail trade -- New Jersey
Photographs
New Jersey
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Detailed Description of Collection
- General Files, 1939-1998 and undated
  - Clippings and publicity, 1940-1966 (Box 1)
  - Clippings re Judith van Schoyck, 1971-1973
  - Color Effects (Diane van Schoyck), 1993
  - Correspondence, 1940-1961
  - Doris and Roger, biographical--college years, 1939-1942, (2 folders)
  - Doris Bryn modeling contracts, 1943-1951
  - Doris Bryn modeling examples, 1940s-1960s, (2 folders)
  - Franklin Lakes National Bank, 1980s
  - Interviews, 1942-1966 and undated, (2 folders)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940s-1998 (Box 2)
  - Mr. R (J.C. Penney fashion line), 1969 and undated
  - Photographs
    - Doris Bryn, undated, (4 folders)
    - Doris and Roger van Schoyck, undated
    - Miscellaneous, 1940s-1950s and undated, (2 folders)
    - Roger van Schoyck, undated
    - Roger Van S. displays, undated
    - Negatives
  - Real estate ventures, 1990-1998
- Roger van S.1939-1998 and undated
  - Advertising, 1950s-1966 (Box 2)
  - Advertising spreads, undated (Box 3)
  - Appearance advertising, 1964 and undated
  - Authentics line of fashion jewelry, 1950s-1960s
  - Clippings and publicity, 1939-1998 and undated
  - Company history, 1966 and undated
  - Designs, 1976-1988
  - Fashion labels, undated
  - Meeting notes, 1968-1969
  - Miscellaneous, 1951-1966 and undated
  - Newsprint advertising, 1950s-1960s, (3 folders)
  - Overseas operations, 1974-1988
  - Print advertising, 1950s-1960s, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Printed material, 1956-1985
  - Publicity, 1950s-1984
  - Shoes, 1950s-1960s
  - Store displays, undated
  - The Business World of Roger van Schoyck, undated
- Large Format Materials
  - Doris Bryn photographs, 1940s-1960s and undated, (6 folders) (Box 5)
  - Doris Bryn sketches by various artists, undated (Box 6)
  - Doris Bryn modeling examples, 1940s
  - Roger van S. advertising scrapbook, 1950s-1965, (5 folders)
  - Roger van S. advertising/fashion line scrapbook, undated (Box 7)
  - Roger van S. newsprint advertising, 1940s-1960s, (5 folders) (Box 8)
  - Doris Bryn clippings, 1941-1980 (Box 9)
  - Doris Bryn modeling examples, 1942-1950s, (2 folders)
  - Doris Bryn Photograph Workshop feature, Summer issue1950
  - Roger van S. Leather Industries of America awards, 1966
  - Roger van S. newsprint advertising, 1940s-1960s, (5 folders)
  - Doris Bryn modeling examples, 1944-1964, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Roger van S. clippings and publicity, 1941-1966
  - Roger van S. magazine advertising, 1949-1969, (1-2 of 6 folders)
  - Roger van S. magazine advertising, 1949-1969, (3-6 of 6 folders) (Box 11)
  - Roger van S. newsprint advertising, 1940s-1960s, (3 folders)
  - Roger van S. magazine advertising, 1940s-1960s, (3 folders) (Box 12)
  - Roger van S. publicity packets, undated, (2 folders)